Since 2003, a special type of scam targeting the elderly
Od roku 2003 w Japonii króluje biorące na cel osoby starsze
called the money transfer scam has proliferated in Japan.
oszustwo zwane „przekrętem na przelew”.
Financial damages increased every year, reaching 56.5 billion yen in 2014.
Straty finansowe rosną z roku na rok. W 2014 r. wynosiły 56,5 miliarda jenów.
Now, in 2019, scammers have changed their techniques,
W 2019 roku oszuści zmienili metody,
and the damage continues.
w dalszym ciągu okradając obywateli.
Scamming isn't the worst crime. You can make money and never get caught.
Przekręty to nie zbrodnia. Można zarobić i nie wpaść.
Now, a question for everyone.
Mam do was pytanie.
EPISODE 3
ODCINEK 3
Is scamming people a crime?
Czy oszukiwanie ludzi to przestępstwo?
What?
Co?
I think...
Chyba...
it is a crime.
Tak sądzę.
But...
Ale...
That's correct.
Masz rację.
We're fooling people and taking their money.
Oszukujemy ludzi i zabieramy im pieniądze.
Of course that's a crime.
Oczywiście, że to przestępstwo.
But wait a moment.
Mimo to...
There are lots of people in the world who do the exact same thing, but legally.
Masa ludzi na świecie robi to samo legalnie.
For example, people who say, "You'll get a job if you do this"
Na przykład ci, którzy obiecują pracę,
and then sell expensive textbooks.
jeśli kupicie drogie podręczniki.
Have any of you experienced that?
Spotkaliście się z tym?
I encountered that at an English language school.
Ja tak, w szkole języka angielskiego.
Right? There are plenty of businesses like that.
Prawda? Takich firm jest mnóstwo.
They sell you jewelry and make you take out millions in loans,
Sprzedają wam biżuterię, namawiają na milionowe pożyczki,
or they sell questionable health products at exorbitant prices.
sprzedają pseudomedyczną ściemę w kosmicznych cenach.
Aren't most of those scams?
To nie są przekręty?
So why aren't they arrested?
To dlaczego nikt ich nie aresztuje?
Why is that?
Dlaczego?
Because...
Bo...
customers have consented to buying those things?
klienci dobrowolnie kupują ich produkty?
You're smart, aren't you?
Mądrala z ciebie.
It's legal, so they can't complain.
To legalny proceder, nie podlega zażaleniom.
Do you really think that?
Tak sądzisz?
I used to work at a real estate company.
Pracowałem kiedyś w nieruchomościach.
There were customers we knew couldn't afford homes,
Niektórzy klienci wiedzieli, że nie stać ich na dom,
but we still talked them into buying expensive properties.
a mimo to namawialiśmy ich na zakup drogich nieruchomości.
Of course, it was legal.
Oczywiście legalnie.
But...
Ale...
later on, I learned that...
później dowiadywałem się,
they went bankrupt or that their families fell apart,
że ci ludzie bankrutowali, tracili rodziny.
and I couldn't sleep at night.
Nie mogłem spać.
Compared to that, this work is heaven.
W porównaniu z tym jesteśmy aniołami.
Want to know why?
Wiecie dlaczego?
Stealing two million yen from a poor person...
Porównajcie kradzież dwóch milionów od biedaka...
...with zero yen in savings...
...który nie ma nic...
EXPLOITATION
WYZYSK
...compared to stealing two million yen...
...i kradzież tej samej kwoty...
...from an ultra-rich person...
...od bogacza,
with 20 million in savings.
który ma na koncie 20 baniek.
SEIZURE
KONFISKATA
Which of these is the bigger crime?
Co jest gorsze?
Which makes you feel sicker?
Z czym będzie wam źle?
In scams, we aim to get two million from each target.
Od każdego celu chcemy uzyskać dwa miliony.
For a poor person, that amount would make him hang himself.
Biedak mógłby się przez to powiesić.
However, an old person will throw that away with one phone call.
Staruszek natomiast wyda taką sumę lekką ręką.
Why? Because they have financial flexibility.
Dlaczego? Bo ma płynność finansową.
Do you understand?
Rozumiecie?
More than half of the money in Japan is held by those over the age of 60.
Ponad połowa majątku w Japonii jest w rękach osób po 60.
Can you believe that? Of course you can. You saw it yourselves!
Uwierzycie? Pewnie, przecież widzieliście.
The elderly are living it up in the middle of the day.
Tacy bawią się życiem.
It's these people who are our targets.
To oni będą naszym celem.
But...
Ale...
But didn't they work hard and save money when they were young?
Przecież zarobili na to ciężką pracą w młodości.
Yeah, maybe.
Być może.
But unlike today,
Ale wtedy
the economy was prosperous back then.
gospodarka kwitła.
Do you hear me?
Rozumiecie?
The average bank account of a person over 60...
Każda osoba po 60 roku życia ma na koncie
contains 20 million yen.
średnio 20 milionów.
They get a pension of 180,000 a month.
Otrzymują 180 tysięcy emerytury.
Did you hear that? 180,000 yen.
Dociera to do was? 180.
That's more than the young get for working hard.
To więcej niż młodzi za ciężką pracę.
And when you get older, how much will your pensions be?
Ile wy będziecie dostawać,
I'm not even paying into it.
Ja nawet nie odkładam.
We can't.
Nie mamy jak.
Right? More than that, the elderly save 40% of the pension they get.
Prawda? Starsze osoby odkładają co najmniej 40% emerytury.
So the money left over when they die,
Po śmierci,
including property,
licząc nieruchomości,
averages to 30 million yen.
zostawiają 30 baniek.
Thirty million?
Trzydzieści milionów?
It's unbelievable, isn't it? I can't believe it myself!
Niewiarygodne, co? Sam nie wierzę.
Why aren't the elderly using all this money?
Dlaczego tego nie wydają?
Why don't they try to share it with all of you who are suffering?
Czemu nie podzielą się z potrzebującymi?
That's why the elderly are a cancer on Japan.
Dlatego starsi ludzie to rak toczący Japonię.
Because of them, our country is sick.
Przez nich nasza ojczyzna choruje.
They are the richest race in the world
Są najbogatsi na świecie,
and the stingiest.
a najbardziej skąpi.
That's right, they're a different race. A different species.
To zupełnie inny gatunek.
We don't feel an ounce of guilt
Nie będziemy odczuwać winy,
for taking two million from their type.
zabierając takim dwa miliony.
In fact,
Tak naprawdę
we're proud of what we do.
będziemy z tego dumni.
I'll say it again.
Powtórzę to.
You can make money doing this.
Możecie sporo zarobić.
There are people who make 50 million a year
Niektórzy zarabiają rocznie 50 milionów,
and some who even make 100 million.
a nawet sto.
Sure, occasionally someone is arrested.
Jasne, ktoś może trafić za kraty,
But they were no good from the start. They were bad at their jobs.
ale tylko ktoś, kto nie radził sobie od początku.
But we're different.
My jesteśmy inni.
I will protect you all with my life.
Ja będę was chronił za wszelką cenę.
That is my job as your leader.
To moje zadanie.
So in return, will you all trust me with your lives?
Czy w zamian za to powierzycie mi życie?
I want to work with you.
Pragnę z wami pracować.
Sincerely.
Szczerze.
Whether you join me or not is up to you.
Sami zadecydujcie, czy chcecie do mnie dołączyć.
I won't force you.
Nikt nie będzie was zmuszał.
But let me say this.
Powiem jedno.
Scamming isn't the worst crime.
Przekręty to nie zbrodnia.
You'll make money and you won't get caught.
Zarobicie i nikt was nie złapie.
If you hang on to this job,
Jeśli wybierzecie tę pracę,
you'll never have to feel insecure
zapomnicie o niepewności,
or unfulfilled or frustrated ever again.
braku spełnienia i frustracji.
You five have been chosen.
My wybraliśmy waszą piątkę.
That is all.
To tyle.
If they scare you all of the sudden or if the story is too good to be true,
Jeśli ktoś was nagle wystraszy
please be cautioned.
nie dajcie się nabrać.
...claiming to be a family member...
...podając się za członka rodziny...
...before you send money...
...zanim wyślecie pieniądze...
...report immediately...
...natychmiast zgłosić...
Money transfer scams...
Kolejne przekręty...
Wait!
Czekaj!
Like this.
Zrób tak.
You'll leave prints.
Zostawisz odciski.
Right! Thanks.
Jasne, dzięki.
Good morning!
Dzień dobry!
Okay then, time for the daily inspection.
Czas na inspekcję.
As you already know, all you're allowed to bring here
Jak wiecie, wolno wam przynosić do pracy
is cigarettes, money and your work phones.
papierosy, gotówkę i telefony służbowe.
If you bring anything else,
Jeśli przyniesiecie coś innego,
you'll get the beating of your life. Got it?
skopię was jak psy. Zrozumiano?
Yes, sir!
Tak jest!
-Everyone's clear! -All right, then!
- Wszystko jasne! - Doskonale!
Next, today's speech.
Czas na dzisiejszą mowę.
Seimiya!
Seimiya!
Yes, sir!
Tak jest!
At my local supermarket...
W moim supermarkecie...
So, there's this supermarket,
Obok mnie jest supermarket.
and in the deli section,
W dziale delikatesów
-an old man-- -Hurry it up!
- starszy pan... - Szybko!
I'm sorry! An old man was taking the free soy sauce packages
Przepraszam! Starszy pan brał próbki sosu sojowego
and putting them in his bag!
i wkładał je do torby.
When the clerk told him to stop,
Sprzedawczyni zwróciła mu uwagę,
he started yelling at her,
a on na nią nawrzeszczał.
and it really pissed me off!
Wkurzyłem się!
Unforgivable!
Niedopuszczalne!
Down with the elderly disease!
Staruchy do piachu!
-Let's get them, boys! -Yes, sir!
- Do dzieła, panowie! - Tak jest!
Hello. You've reached the Sato residence.
Sato, słucham.
Hello.
Halo?
Hello, this is Hitoshi.
Mówi Hitoshi.
I'm in trouble...
Mam kłopoty...
-I'm in trouble... -Hitoshi?
- Kłopoty. - Hitoshi?
What happened? Aren't you at work?
Co się stało? Nie jesteś w pracy?
This is a three-role type scenario that requires three players.
To scenka dla trzech osób,
The first player is the son, and after he says his name,
Pierwszy wciela się w syna, który się przedstawia
he doesn't say anything else.
i nie mówi nic więcej.
In fact, the target will get suspicious if he talks too much,
Inaczej ofiara nabierze podejrzeń,
so he has to be careful.
więc trzeba uważać.
Also, we don't use the "Hey, Mom, it's me" technique.
Nie używamy też metody z mówieniem: „Mamo, to ja”.
Instead, we get hold of a family register with names and family relations.
Zamiast tego zdobywamy listę członków rodziny.
You are Sato's mother,
Pani Sato,
and I am... I'm Takayama, one of your son's coworkers.
nazywam się Takayama, pracuję z pani synem.
Your son is in big trouble!
Narobił sobie kłopotów!
The second player, the complainant, is the rager.
Druga osoba jest wściekła i skarży się na pierwszą.
He's an adulterer!
To cudzołożnik!
He slept with my wife, and now she's pregnant with his child!
Spał z moją żoną i zrobił jej bachora!
His job is to get angry and bombard the target with yelling.
Ma się wściekać i przytłoczyć rozmówcę wrzaskami.
Hello, excuse me.
Przepraszam.
Is this Hitoshi's mother?
Jest pani mamą Hitoshiego?
I am Takayama-san's lawyer Sugimura.
Sugimura, adwokat pana Takayamy.
The third person plays a lawyer or cop.
Trzecia osoba gra prawnika lub gliniarza.
He's the only person who acts calm.
Tylko ona zachowuje spokój.
He gets between the complainant and the target,
Wtrąca się w rozmowę,
brings up the possibility of a trial or termination and suggests a settlement.
wspomina o procesie i proponuje ugodę.
As you can hear, my client is very upset.
Sama pani słyszy, że mój klient jest wściekły.
-I'm sorry! -Hey!
Przepraszam!
The rager is the key.
Pieniacz jest kluczowy.
Aggressively threatening the unsettled target is very effective.
Agresywne groźby są bardzo skuteczne.
I'll kill you!
Zatłukę cię!
Give me the phone!
Daj mi telefon!
Listen, old lady, this isn't something he can pay his way out of!
Posłuchaj, paniusiu, tak łatwo się z tego nie wywinie!
I'm going to tell everyone at work! He won't get away with this! He's through!
Powiem wszystkim w pracy! Już po nim!
Let go of me!
Puszczajcie!
Excuse me, it's me again.
Przepraszam, to znów ja.
Who was that just now?
Co tam się dzieje?
Well...
Cóż...
That was Takayama-san's brother.
To brat pana Takayamy.
More importantly, we should settle this before it goes any further.
Powinniśmy dążyć do ugody, zanim sprawa zostanie rozdmuchana.
Let me talk to my son.
Proszę dać mi syna.
Well, that's...
To...
Please, I want to talk to my son!
Błagam!
Hello, Mom.
Mamo?
What have you done?
Coś ty narobił?
Will money fix this?
Możesz im zapłacić?
I'll pay if that will fix it!
Dam pieniądze, jeśli to pomoże!
So...
Mogę...
Did you just call me "Mom"?
Powiedziałeś: „Mamo”?
You've never called me "Mom" before.
Nigdy tak nie mówiłeś.
You've called me "Mommy" since you were little!
Od dziecka nazywasz mnie mamusią!
If things go south, we hang up. We never go deeper than we have to.
Jak coś idzie nie tak, rozłączamy się. Nie drążymy niepotrzebnie.
Why are you idiots improvising?
Co to za improwizacja, kretyni?
At first, we kept on failing like this.
Na początku nam nie szło.
Still, they always made sure the players were paid.
Mimo to nam płacili.
The basic salary was 500,000 a month, plus transportation fees.
Dostawaliśmy 500 000 podstawy i dodatek na transport.
We also get 10% if we succeed.
Do tego 10% premii za sukces.
So, if we carried out a two million yen scam, we'd get 200,000.
Za przekręt na dwie bańki dostawaliśmy 200 tysięcy.
I've started to believe that the 50 million a year
Zacząłem wierzyć, że obiecane 50 milionów rocznie
that Kanbe promised isn't a lie.
wcale nie jest niemożliwe.
We'll send someone to your house right away.
Za chwilę kogoś do pani wyślemy.
Are we in agreement that this will be a settlement fee?
Zgadza się pani na taką kwotę ugody?
If so, this becomes a civil case and the police will no longer be involved.
W takim przypadku będzie to sprawa cywilna bez udziału policji.
-Yes, please. -Thank you very much.
- Tak. - Dziękuję.
Thank you...
Dziękuję.
We did it!
Udało się!
Mom, the police...
Mamo, policja...
Mom! I'm so sorry!
Mamo, tak mi przykro!
He slept with my wife!
Spał z moją żoną!
Because it's an accident, it's a criminal case, not a civil case.
Jest to sprawa karna, a nie cywilna.
He'll drop the charges if we can come to a settlement.
Wycofa zarzuty, jeśli dojdziemy do porozumienia.
We aren't allowed to deposit the money we make in the bank.
Nie możemy wpłacać zarobków do banku.
Drugs and alcohol are forbidden as well,
Nie możemy też kupować narkotyków i alkoholu,
because they might draw attention from tax authorities or the police.
bo zwrócimy na siebie uwagę skarbówki albo policji.
That's not a problem for me
Dla mnie to nie problem,
because my father's treatment is extremely expensive.
bo leczenie taty jest bardzo kosztowne.
I have no time for fun.
Nie mam czasu na zabawę.
Thank you.
Dziękuję.
-What's that? -Isn't it great?
- Co to? - Super, co?
It's a gateau chocolate cake.
Babka czekoladowa.
Happy birthday!
Wszystkiego najlepszego!
-Wrong guess, idiot. -Is this your birthday, Mom?
- Nie zgadłeś, kretynie. - To twoje urodziny?
-Okay, so what is it?
- To co?
-We're celebrating your new job! -Congrats!
- Twoja nowa praca! - Gratulacje!
-Thank her for the cake! -Don't worry about it.
- Podziękuj jej za ciasto. - Nie ma sprawy.
I got a discount at work.
Dostałam zniżkę.
-So it's cheap. -Dummy.
- Było tanie. - Głupek.
-Say thank you. -Yeah, dummy.
- Podziękuj. - Właśnie.
Say thank you.
Podziękuj.
Do you know how?
Umiesz dziękować?
I can't tell whether you're congratulating me or making fun of me.
Gratulujecie mi czy ze mnie kpicie?
Making fun of you.
Kpimy.
That's what I thought.
Tak myślałem.
Makoto. I'm really happy for you.
Cieszę się, Makoto.
Thanks.
Dziękuję.
Sit down.
Usiądź.
You all are very precious to me.
Bardzo was cenię.
You're my treasures.
Moje skarby.
To be honest, when I first saw you,
Gdy was ujrzałem,
I didn't think you'd become professional players so quickly.
nie sądziłem, że tak szybko opanujecie tę sztukę.
I'm really impressed.
Jestem pod wrażeniem.
Today's party is, well,
Dzisiejszą imprezą
my way of thanking you from the bottom of my heart.
chciałbym wam podziękować
Please, enjoy yourselves!
Bawcie się dobrze!
Thank you.
Dziękujemy.
Tonight is on Kanbe-san!
Dziś stawia pan Kanbe!
You're free to take any of these ladies home.
Możecie zabrać panienki do domu.
They're all on the pill, so you can even go bareback!
Biorą pigułki, więc nie musicie uważać.
But let me warn you!
Ale uwaga!
The girls are only for tonight.
Oferta obowiązuje tylko dziś.
After tonight, if you try
Jeśli kolejnego dnia
to spend money on them or keep them around, I'll kill you!
wydacie na nie forsę albo będziecie się zabawiać, zatłukę was.
Don't give out your numbers or your addresses! And...
Nie dawajcie im numerów ani adresów!
the most important thing is the job! Got it?
Najważniejsza jest praca. Jasne?
Yes!
Tak!
Now it's time to party!
Czas na zabawę!
Hello.
Cześć.
Himeka, what are you doing here?
Co tu robisz, Himeka?
What about you, Makoto? What company is this?
A ty, Makoto? Co to za firma?
Well...
Cóż...
I was told not to ask any questions, but...
Miałam nie zadawać pytań, ale...
More importantly, have you heard anything from Shotaro?
Co ważniejsze, Shotaro się odzywał?
What?
Co?
Look at this.
Patrz.
LIVING IT UP WITH SHOTARO
JA I SHOTARO SIĘ BAWIMY
I hate that asshole!
Co za dupek.
Who's this girl? Someone you know?
Znasz tę dziewczynę?
My friend from Osaka.
To koleżanka z Osaki.
She said they hooked up. Can you believe him?
Ponoć się spiknęli. Dasz wiarę?
So, Shotaro is in Osaka?
Shotaro jest w Osace?
Not anymore, I think.
Chyba już nie.
He left the next day and disappeared.
Wyjechał dzień później. Zniknął.
He's the absolute worst.
Co za baran.
I'll kill him!
Zabiję go!
I'm going to kill him!
Zatłukę gnoja!
Hey, hey, hey! Calm down!
Uspokój się!
Here, have a drink.
Napij się.
The door wasn't locked.
Było otwarte.
Here.
Proszę.
Hey,
Wiesz,
you really should lock the door.
powinnaś zamykać drzwi.
Are you okay?
Wszystko gra?
Yamada-san?
Pan Yamada?
Well, well, well!
No proszę!
What a surprise. Make yourself at home.
Co za niespodzianka.
Why are you here?
Co tu robicie?
I've got something to ask her.
Mam do niej pytanie.
Thanks for the beer.
Dzięki za piwko.
Thank you!
Dziękuję!
Have you heard from him?
Odzywał się?
-Answer the question! -No.
- Odpowiadaj! - Nie.
She hasn't heard anything.
Nic nie wie.
Well, then...
No cóż.
I guess you'll just have to pay off
W takim razie odpracujesz nam to,
the money he stole.
co ukradł.
Pay off?
Odpracuję?
-I'll get you a great new job. -Outside of Japan though.
- Dostaniesz nową fuchę. - Ale nie w Japonii.
-Yamada-san. -It can't be helped, it's Shotaro's fault.
- Panie Yamada. - To wina Shotara.
Or would you prefer to pay it off instead?
Może sam chcesz to spłacić?
That's not a bad idea.
Dobry pomysł.
You're making a ton of money now, right?
Zarabiasz kupę forsy.
You can afford booze and ladies.
Na wódę i panienki masz.
Who do you have to thank for having the money to do that?
Komu powinieneś za to dziękować?
I...
Ja...
-Go on. -Got it.
- Idziemy. - Tak jest.
-Get up. -Stop!
- Wstawaj. - Dość!
Stop it!
Przestańcie!
-Let me go! -Get up!
- Puśćcie mnie! - Wstawaj!
-Stop! -Please wait.
- Nie! - Zaczekajcie.
Please wait.
Proszę.
What's that?
Co jest?
Please wait!
Zaczekajcie!
So you're saying...
Czyli ty chcesz...
you'll pay his debt?
spłacić jego dług?
Okay then, I'll be in touch about the details.
Dobra, odezwę się.
What's going on?
Co się dzieje?
Who are they?
Kim są ci ludzie?
Makoto, what kind of work are you doing?
Makoto, gdzie ty pracujesz?
Tell me!
Powiedz!
Don't tell anyone about this.
Nikomu o tym nie mów.
Especially not Misaki.
W szczególności Misaki.
Please.
Proszę.
Punk!
Pajac!
Subtitle translation by Marti McElreath
Napisy: Konrad Szabowicz